<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A casket of ievvells and precious pearles Set forth in a funerall sermon, preached in Heckfield Church, at the buriall of a religious young gentleman, Mr. Barnabas Creswell, sonne of Mr. Thomas Creswell Esquire, by Nathanael Cannon, Batchelar in diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4575.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17913)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1683:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A casket of ievvells and precious pearles Set forth in a funerall sermon, preached in Heckfield Church, at the buriall of a religious young gentleman, Mr. Barnabas Creswell, sonne of Mr. Thomas Creswell Esquire, by Nathanael Cannon, Batchelar in diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Nathanael Newbery, at the Starre vnder St. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Creswell, Barnabas, d. 1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CASKET OF IEVVELS and precious PEARLES. Set forth in a FVNERALL Sermon, Preached in <hi>Heckfield</hi> Church, at the Buriall of a Religious young Gentleman, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Barnabas Creſwell,</hi> Sonne of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Creſwell</hi> Eſquire, By NATHANAEL CANNON, Batchelar in Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. de Temp. Ser. 49.</hi>
               </bibl> Dies noſter Dominus Chriſtus non facit occaſum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> at the Starre vnder St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull and Chriſtian yoake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowes, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Stampe,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">irs</hi>. <hi>Iane Stampe</hi> his Wife, <hi>Nathaniel Cannon</hi> wiſheth true Comforts, externall, internall, and eternall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you Both, as partners in loſſe, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, I tender this Treatiſe, and yet I am to ſpeake vnto you two, who are but one, apart,
<pb facs="tcp:16364:3"/>concerning this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, he called you Father, by a courſe of Law, and yet with conſcience declared himſelfe a very childe.</p>
            <p>For if obedience, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and daily diligence might beget loue, then needs muſt he be a beloued Sonne, who was all this to you for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>To you, (his deare Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) hee was a right <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas;</hi> which is by ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, a Sonne of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which you had no ſmall meaſure, both from his life and death.</p>
            <p>He honoured you, you lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him; he comforted you,
<pb facs="tcp:16364:3"/>you tendered him; and this was the mutuall intercourſe betwixt you, vntill GOD tooke him from you.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelfe, who at his Funerall read the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of our mortality, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many bands of Chriſtianity, wherewith all the faithfull are linked and conioyned together, there are other eſpeciall motiues to make you and yours neare and deare to me.</p>
            <p>For firſt you were a good Inſtrument vnder GOD, both to comfort and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell mee in that calling whereunto the Lord hath
<pb facs="tcp:16364:4"/>appointed mee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you, and that worthy Gentleman, my Brother, Maſter <hi>Creſwell,</hi> who is falne aſleepe, were not wanting to mee and mine, but made your houſe vnto vs, as the houſe of <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> was vnto <hi>Paul,</hi> a place of great refreſhing, <hi>2 Tim. 1.16.</hi> Now as the Prophet ſaith vnto the <hi>Sunamyte,</hi> who had prouided a Chamber, a Table, a Stoole, and a Candleſticke for the man of God, <hi>2 Kings 4.13. thou haſt been careful for vs, but what may I do for thee?</hi> ſo ſay I, what ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:16364:4"/>be done for you by mee? Surely, vnleſſe it be in the courſe of my calling, to pray with you, and for you, and ſometimes as God offers occaſion to preſent ſome part of my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours vnto you; loe this is all, I can doe nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let mee pay my debts vnto you after this manner; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that you both, with diuers others haue deſired, that this Sermon, Preached at the Funerall of this faithfull ſeruant of God, and deere Son of yours might ſee the light.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:5"/>
            <p>Yet let mee not robbe you (louing Brother) of your deſires in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this your eſpeciall requeſt, that hee whom you had imprinted in your heart, might be put in Print at your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; which is done by way of Dedication to you, and her who is a part of you, my deere Siſter.</p>
            <p>Here ſhall you take a view of the Saints, and of their condition, who are the precious Iewels lockt vp in the Casket of this Scripture.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe your Childe was one of theſe, a rich
<pb facs="tcp:16364:5"/>Diamond, whoſe ground being Chriſt, muſt needes haue the light both of grace and glory.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore, (<hi>Iobs</hi> giuer and taker) which Text hee quoteth in the caſe of Children, <hi>God giueth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and God taketh, bleſſed be the name of the Lord, Iob 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will bleſſe him, he will bleſſe you; our leaſt ſubmiſsion, brings great conſolation.</p>
            <p>Yeeld Siſter, yeeld; and God grant you the true comfort of thoſe branches yet in being.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:6"/>
            <p>God bleſſe them, and make his face to ſhine vpon them, that they may liue to doe worthily in <hi>Ephrata,</hi> and be famous in <hi>Bethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Ruth <hi>4.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Subſcribed by your louing Brother in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Nathanael Cannon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16364:6"/>
            <head>Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 116. Verſe 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole world in her full age is but a Kalnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of yeares and dayes, as for Man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that little world, he brings his yeares to an end as it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16364:7"/>were a tale that is told; <hi>Nam vita noſtra ſimiles eſt Rotae,</hi> ſaith <hi>(Zanchius)</hi> vpon the fourth to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> our life, ſaith he, is like a wheele; <hi>modo in ſuprema, modo in infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma parte verſamur;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaith he, we are ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſometimes falling; now wee are at the very top and height of our comforts, &amp; by and by, downe againe in the depth of our ſorrowes; at length in the tranſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this whirling wheele, that life that earſt was all aloft, ſhall with one gaſpe, lay it ſelfe all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16364:7"/>along: What ſhall we ſay to this? the Heauens doe many times grow blacke and cloudy, and yet cleere againe; the earth moues not at all, yet hath his being; the Seas, they ebbe &amp; flowe, but haue returnes; yea, the very plants and trees let fall their leaſe, but keepe their life, for as <hi>Iob</hi> 14. obſerues, There is hope of a tree though it be cut downe, yet by the ſcent of water it may bud and ſprout forth againe; but as for man, the man of earth, for ſo he is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, as <hi>(Chryſoſtome)</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16364:8"/>obſerues in his 12. <hi>Hom.</hi> in <hi>Gen. Homo rectè terra apellatur, quia prorſus eſt terrenus:</hi> he may well be called earth, that is ſo earthly. Alas, this man, as <hi>Iob</hi> notes, falles ſicke and dyes; gone he is, with a <hi>nunquam rediturus,</hi> the eye that hath ſeene him, ſhall ſee him no more; <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimur &amp; morimur,</hi> wee liue, wee dye, <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee neede not turne our bookes to proue this point, for in Gods ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Library,</hi> which is the world, there are two <hi>Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> Bookes, the one <hi>liber
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16364:8"/>Creaturarum,</hi> the booke of the Creatures, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>liber Scripturarum,</hi> the booke of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in both theſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes it is written, that <hi>Death</hi> hath a <hi>Habeas-Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> for vs all: As for that of the Creatures, it ſpeakes vnto vs in the matter of our mortality, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> doth in the 19. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> touching Gods glory, <hi>One day tels another, and one night certifieth another and there is neither ſpeech nor language vnder the heauens, but the voyce of Gods glory is heard amongſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16364:9"/>them;</hi> ſo verily, one day tels another, and one night certifies another, &amp; there is neither ſpeech nor language vnder the heauens, but the voyce of death is heard amongſt them. As for that of the Scriptures, we know that all Scripture is giuen by inſpiration from God, and is profitable to teach as the Apoſtle witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Each leafe doth reade a lecture to our life, teaching vs ſo to liue the life of the righteous, that wee may die the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16364:9"/>wee may ſay of the Scriptures as the Apoſtle doth of the ſtarres, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>one ſtarre,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>differeth from another in glory;</hi> ſo doubtleſſe, one Scripture may giue more light vnto a matter then another, and one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may yeeld more comfort againſt death then another; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, then let me ſay for this Text, that it doth ſo prepare, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſolue the faithfull, ſo perfume their graues, which are, their beds, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.2. that they knowing themſelues to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16364:10"/>bee the Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, and the ſpirit of God bearing witneſſe vnto theirs, that they are his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. Yea, his deere darlings and precious Iewels, they then feele that comfort wherof the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they liue or dye they are the Lords, and they apprehend their aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in Chriſt Ieſus, who as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to him both in life and death, Phil.</hi> 1.21. This makes the Saints with old <hi>Simeon,</hi> ready to cry, <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16364:10"/>ſeruant depart in peace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy word, for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:</hi> Now the Saints haue the ſame obiect to looke vpon, and the ſame ſubiect to ſpeake on; and muſt not they then bee precious, who ſhall bee heyres of ſaluation? Such honour haue all the Saints, of whoſe happy ſtate and condition, my Text here ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>Let mee therefore ſay thus much of this porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scripture, that it is very ſeaſonable for the occaſion, and very ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his perſon that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16364:11"/>here lyes before vs, of whom I doubt not to pronounce him the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. &amp; ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt; and therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Now come wee to the worke wee haue in hand, that ſo wee may ſee how this Text takes place in point of Coherence with tha reſt of the Pſalme.</p>
            <p>The voyce of Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing doth with a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall trumpet ſoundforth the praiſe of God in this Pſalme, wherein (<hi>Dauid</hi> who was the ſweet Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Iſraell) hath many notes of thankful remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16364:11"/>for the manifolde deliuerances that GOD had vouchſafed vnto him; but more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee inſtances in that mercy that the Lord ſhewed in keeping him from <hi>Saul,</hi> who hunted after his life in the deſart of <hi>Maon:</hi> And in the 3. verſe, he tels vs that when the ſorrowes of death had compaſſed him round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, then hee began to lay hold on God, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe that neither <hi>Saul,</hi> nor any of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rgents, ſhould eyther catch or kill him without that diuine permiſſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16364:12"/>which did watch ouer him: and there fore hee will put his life into the hands of God, and vpon that very ground, he will ſet vp his reſt: which hee doth in the 7. verſe, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne O my ſoule vnto thy reſt;</hi> and becauſe they are vnworthy of future bleſſings, who are not thankfull for former, hee therefore comes in the 12. &amp; 13. verſes with his <hi>quid retribuam Domino?</hi> what ſhal I render to the Lord for all his mercies? then the cup of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt bee mentioned, and the vowes muſt bee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16364:12"/>paide: making my Text the reaſon of all this; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord will take ſuch care, both of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſoules, of the liues and deaths of his Saints, that whether hee preſerue them from the hands of Tyrants, or elſe ſuffer them to be euill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated or perſecuted, that ſo God may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, this ſhall be ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprinted in the hearts of the faithfull, that they are right deere and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of God. And thus much ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Analyſis of the whole Pſalme, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16364:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the particular ſenſe and meaning of the Text it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now it remaines, that wee take the Text aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and note vnto you the diuident Branches thereof:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Obſerue the diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that ſo their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, may put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption; and that in their earthly peregrina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they may paſſe from the Kingdome of Grace, to the Kingdome of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Obſerue the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of the Saints
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16364:13"/>with God: to earthly men, they are but meane, baſe, and contemptible, in the ſight of this world; but in the ſight of God, right deere and precious; and as they value <hi>Dauids</hi> life in the 2 of <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. <hi>thy life,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is worth tenne thouſand of ours:</hi> So indeed, one faithfull Seruant of the Lord, is worth tenne thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the ſight of God, for they are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his ſight.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Ratione praetij,</hi> by reaſon of the price that was paide to redeeme their ſoules withall, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16364:14"/>that was, <hi>the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle witneſſeth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 Chap. Verſe 19. <hi>Potens non perdet,</hi> ſaith a Father, <hi>quod pecunia emebat,</hi> A great man will not looſe that which hee purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with his money, <hi>Nec Chriſtus perdet quod ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine emebat,</hi> then may wee bee ſure that Chriſt will not looſe that which hee purchaſed with his bloud: that precious bloud.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Ratione tituli,</hi> they are precious by reaſon of their title that God hath giuen them, they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16364:14"/>the Saynts of God. What greater honor can there bee? Crownes and Scepters comes ſhort of this, vnles they be within the compaſſe of this: <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauldry</hi> hath no ſuch ſcut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions: <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> hath the beſt Coate; the Creſt or helme, it is ſaluation it ſelfe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no meruaile though <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour did preferre his Chriſtianity before his Crowne, <hi>Mallem me eſſe Chriſtianum quàm Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Ratione proemij,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious they are by reaſon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16364:15"/>of the reward laide vp for them; they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes made to them, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>They la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not in vaine, as the men of this world doe:</hi> Doubtleſſe man, ſaith <hi>Dauid, diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine, he heapeth vp ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and cannot tell who ſhall gather them:</hi> But as for the Saints, when they haue finiſhed their courſe, there is laide vp for them a crowne of glory; yea, <hi>for all them that loue the comming of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. Loe thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16364:15"/>haue wee lookt vpon the Tree and the Branches, the Text and the parts; now let vs gather the fruit thereof, beginning firſt with our firſt Branch, which is the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a hedge made about <hi>Iob</hi> the iuſt, which doth much trouble the Diuel, inſomuch that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> cannot come at him, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.10. nor yet the gates of hell preuaile againſt him, what is this but Gods prouidence which wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ouer the righteous, and ſo protects that a hayre fals not from their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16364:16"/>heads without it; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it is that <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> cheares vp the hearts of the faithfull thus, <hi>Si ſic cuſtodiantur ſuperflua tua in quanta ſecuritate eſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma tua?</hi> If ſaith hee, the haires of thy head and the leaſt part of thy body be ſo kept, in what ſafety is thy ſoule preſerued?</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this keeping out of Sathan, by the moundes of Gods mercy, yet wee haue no <hi>quare impedit</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death, nothing keepes it out; for the very Saints who are ſo deare in the ſight of God, euen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16364:16"/>they muſt dye: the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is irreuocable, all the children of <hi>Adam</hi> are within compaſſe of it, for in him, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. in <hi>Adam</hi> al men dye. Here then let vs erect our firſt pillar from this firſt poynt.</p>
            <p>The very hieres of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, amongſt others, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> are ſubiect to diſſolution: though they be the lords Iewels, and pretious in his ſight, yet euen they muſt lay downe their earthly Tabernacles: thus ſaith the ſcriptures.
<note place="margin">Proofes of the Doctrine</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is a ſtatute vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the liues of all fleſh,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16364:17"/>
               <hi>ſtatutum eſt omnibus mori,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>it is appointed for all men to dye and after comes the iudgement:</hi> Not onely <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſells himſelfe to commit wickedneſſe, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.37. nor <hi>Ierobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> who makes <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſin, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 14.20. nor <hi>Demas,</hi> who forſaketh God to follow the world, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 10. but faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> Godly <hi>Dorcas,</hi> yea <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the friend of Chriſt ſhall fall aſleepe. We will looke ſomewhat particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly vpon ſome of theſe inſtances and begin with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16364:17"/>
               <hi>Dorcas,</hi> of whom we reade, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. verſe 36. and 37. the holy Ghoſt reports the place where ſhee dwelt, <hi>Ioppa:</hi> this woman was by profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a Diſciple; that is, a follower and ſcholler of Chriſt Ieſus: then looke into the fruits of her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which is all in all: the Text ſaith, that ſhee was full of good workes, ſhe did abound in them, &amp; yet this good &amp; godly Matron falles ſicke and dyes: <hi>Lazarus</hi> who is ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>friend</hi> of Chriſt, fals aſleepe; a gentle and comfortable expreſſion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16364:18"/>of our death, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.11. <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom God will make a Secretary to his intentions, becauſe he is ſo carefull to bring vp his family in the feare of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. euen this Father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhall fall aſleepe, and yeeld vp the ſpirit <hi>in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Domini,</hi> into the hands of that God that gaue it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.8. What ſhall I ſay of old <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Patriarches, of <hi>Moſes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Ioſhua, Samuel, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and the reſt; all which are gone downe into the graue, notwithſtanding their gifts and graces
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16364:18"/>from aboue? Let not this ſeeme ſtrange, whereby that any ſhould take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to diſpute with God, and to aske, then what is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Saints, and ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> ſeeing all muſt dye? Perchance the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion will ariſe, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Spouſe of Chriſt is put to it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.9. who when ſhee had ſpoken at large, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the royall dignities of her Bridegroome, the queſtion is askt; <hi>What is thy beloued more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beloued, that thou doſt ſo extol him?</hi> So it may be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16364:19"/>ſaid, what priuiledge haue the Saints aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſeeing they muſt dye as well as others? The Solution of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition will rather ſhew it ſelfe in Reaſons, for the Saints diſſolution, then in any other kinde of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reaſon why they ſhould be diſſolued as well as others, is <hi>vt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginalis corruptio deſtrua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> namely, that our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature and originall corruption might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, which cannot be ſo long as we liue vpon earth: wee ſhall haue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16364:19"/>thoſe <hi>Reliquia peccati,</hi> thoſe remnants of ſinne about vs doe what wee can: <hi>velis nollis i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, habitabit Iebuſeus;</hi> doe what wee can, this Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite of corruption will dwell within vs: It is an Inmate which will not be remoued, vntill the houſe of our earthly body bee pulled downe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.2.</p>
            <p>Yea all thoſe <hi>(Romiſh pennances)</hi> of ſcourgings or ſuperſtitious inflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, giues no purgations for it, no not the ſtrict and reſtrictiue courſe of the faithfull who by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16364:20"/>endeuour to bring downe their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and by praier to raiſe vp their ſoules, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding whilſt life laſteth, this ſinfull nature of ours remaineth: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie not, but with a <hi>magis</hi> and a <hi>minus</hi> theſe bleſſed meanes, will take away through Gods bleſſing the exuberancy of it, as a father wel obſerues, <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugari poteſt, exterminari non poteſt,</hi> and in this caſe wee may content our ſelues with the anſwere that God giues <hi>Rebecca</hi> in the 25. of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> ſhe begs of God to know what is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16364:20"/>the reaſon of that extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſtrugling and ſtriuing in her body, and God tels her ſhe hath two manner of people within her, for ſo ſhe had <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſo haue we the fleſh and ſpirit ſtriuing within vs, <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.17. and will not giue ouer, till we giue ouer; and therefore it is expedient for the Saints to dye, that ſo they might be rid of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature, which they ſhall neuer be whilſt they liue.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Reaſon why they ſhould dye as well as others, is, <hi>vt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16364:21"/>fides exerceatur,</hi> that our faith might be exerciſed in the apprehenſion and application of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made ouer to the righteous; for the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith tels vs of a great worke that faith hath to doe; <hi>Faith,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things hoped for, and the euidence of things not ſeene, Heb.</hi> 11.1. Now then that our Faith may at length haue the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe things that it hath beleued, there ſhall be an end of the life of the beleeuer, that ſo poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16364:21"/>may bee had of all thoſe tenents that Faith formerly held: but ſhall wee alwaies beleeue, and not inioy what we haue beleeued? this then muſt be by the ceſſation of life; that is, of this life, that ſo we may inherite life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and then our faith ceaſeth, and we poſſeſſe what hath beene hoped for.</p>
            <p>A third Reaſon why the Saints ſhould dye, <hi>vt perfectio obtineatur,</hi> wee are in <hi>via,</hi> in the way to heauen, but wee are not yet in <hi>patria,</hi> wee looke for that houſe which is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16364:22"/>not made with hands, <hi>but eternall in the heauens,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. Now this we cannot haue on earth; for this cauſe the Saints ſhall dye in the Lord, which is a bleſſed thing; for then <hi>they reſt from their labours, Reuel.</hi> 14. and then comes our perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Wee are now the Sons of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>but it appeares not what we ſhall be,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, loue, and other fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being here but in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. but there we ſhall know perfectly, and obtaine perfection, <hi>when this corruption hath put on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16364:22"/>incorruption,</hi> and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Downe therefore muſt the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacles of the Saints, before wee come to that hauen, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, prepared for vs, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>Theſe things then thus contracted, let the Doctrine be applied and inlarged in the Vſes of it.</p>
            <p>The 1. vſe of this point, is as a voyce to call vpon the faithfull, that ſeeing they muſt bee diſſolued, and yet not when, nor where, nor how, is known vnto vs; let them be ſuch in their conuerſation,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16364:23"/>that they may be ready for their diſſolution; thus <hi>Iob,</hi> the iuſt waites for the day and houre, <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time, will I waite, vntill my changing ſhall come, Iob</hi> 14.14. and olde <hi>Iacob</hi> makes this his breathing-ſtoppe: And the 49. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> hee bleſſeth, and bleſſeth his children, and growes fainter and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then like a ſwounding man, who takes ſomething ſtill to reuiue him; ſo doth hee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>I haue waited for thy ſaluation;</hi> this fetcht life in him as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16364:23"/>it were, and reuiued, euen the remembrance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: thus the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liue as not afraid to dye, as olde <hi>Pollicarpus</hi> tels his tormentors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it vnto vs: <hi>I am this day,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>foureſcore yeares old, and I haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſerued my God:</hi> O bleſſed age, and time well ſpent in the ſeruice of God: for, let vs not thinke to dye the death of the righteous, vnleſſe wee liue the life of the righteous; <hi>our conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then muſt be in heauen, Phil.</hi> 3. and we muſt liue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16364:24"/>here in this world, euen as the Fiſhes doe in the Sea; who though they liue in the ſalt and brack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh water, yet they are freſh; So though we liue in the middeſt of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world, yet muſt wee be freſh and free from the common pollutions of this wicked world: Then ſhall we not fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, as the vngodly doe, for they put too their whole ſtrength, they draw ſins together, and pull them as it were with cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5.18 Let the Saints make ready for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16364:24"/>the comming of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and cry with them, <hi>Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus come quickly, Come quickly Lord Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 2. vſe belonging to this poynt limits our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations; I would not haue you ignorant, ſaith the Apoſtle, concerning thoſe that fall aſleepe, that the ſorrow you take bee not like theirs that haue no hope 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. no, this were to ſhew that we preferred earth before heauen, and the comfort and ioyes of earth, before heauen. We can tell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly what our meanes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16364:25"/>and ſollaces are here on earth, but no eye hath ſeen, nor eare hath heard, nor tongue can tell the ioyes that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that loue him 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Now this limitation for our mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not a prohibition to forbid all mourning, for not to be moued at all, is to ſhew a hard heart, leſſe tender then the bruitiſh creatures, for they will bleate, and mone after one another; but it is the exceſſe of mourning that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, <hi>Non culpamus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymarum
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16364:25"/>effectum, ſed exceſsum,</hi> not the matter ſo much as the manner is ſometimes to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and ſurely when Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſettles, then ſhall we ſee the euill of this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; and when religion ſends arguments after the dead, as <hi>Noah</hi> put forth the Doue vpon the abatement of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, then doe wee, or may wee find all that labour loſt, for they are not loſt that are gone before, <hi>Non ſunt amiſsi, ſed praemiſsi:</hi> and <hi>Iobs</hi> reſtaurations may confirme this vnto vs, for of all that the (<hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16364:26"/>and <hi>Sabeans</hi> tooke from him he had it dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſtored, but for his children, iuſt ſo many as before; and why not chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren two-fold? becauſe the children were not loſt, but at the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould then appeare. With this then I wil cloſe vp this firſt point, and ſo come to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Part of Diuiſion, The Saints acceptation; they are precious in the ſight of God. When <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> was perſwaded that amongſt <hi>Iſhaies</hi> ſonnes the goodlieſt ſhould haue had acceptation, and ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16364:26"/>bin King: God tels him, that he looks not as man doth, on the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or perſon, but on the heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. thence comes our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with God, and for that God will regard vs, and for nothing elſe; <hi>with him there is no reſpect of perſons, Acts</hi> 10. vntill we come to feare him, loue, and obey him; O then he loues vs dearely, then are wee precious in the ſight of God. And hence may we gather towards a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point of Doctrine, teaching vs, that the Lords regard toward vs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16364:27"/>is as our hearts are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: if we feare him, loue him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, then will he delight in vs; we ſhall be precious and deere to him.</p>
            <p>To this the Scriptures doe accord, and to begin with that of the 37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. Verſe, <hi>Marke the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, and behold the iuſt, the latter end of that man ſhall be peace:</hi> as who ſhould ſay, ſuch men are worth the marking. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare whom he will grace or worſhip, <hi>Honorantes honorabo,</hi> they that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16364:27"/>mee, I will honour them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. and as for them that deſpiſe him, hee regards them not, or as the laſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath it, lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemes them: the Lord regards our lowlineſſe and humility, and will aduance the humble and meeke, as the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in her <hi>Magnificat, Luke</hi> 1.48. <hi>He regardeth the lowlineſſe of his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid:</hi> theſe are the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious people in the ſight of God, ſo precious, that if any ſhall hurt or iniure them, it is a battery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God himſelfe; for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16364:28"/>ſo ſaith the Prophet, <hi>He that toucheth you, or hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you, toucheth the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods owne eye, Zach.</hi> 2.8. Hath not <hi>Saul</hi> who afterwards is <hi>Paul,</hi> the queſtion, to the ſame purpoſe? <hi>Acts</hi> 9. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> as who ſhould ſay, I feele the ſtripes, and beare the reproaches done againſt them. O that men thought vpon this as often as they are thornes in the ſides of Gods ſeruants, as often as they play vpon them for their profeſſion! Now in all theſe places wee ſee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16364:28"/>what tender care God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, how deere they are to the LORD; but of all places that of the 25. of <hi>Mathew</hi> 40. where the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his Saints is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>O come yee bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c. when I was ſicke you did viſit mee; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, clothe mee, hungry, feed me; O Lord,</hi> ſay they, <hi>we neuer ſaw thee thus; in as much as you haue done it to one of theſe little ones, you haue done it to mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee will ſtay here my Brethren, and make vſe of this.</p>
            <p>Shall theſe that are ſo precious in the ſight of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16364:29"/>God, be other wiſe in our eyes? <hi>All my delight is in the Saints,</hi> ſayth <hi>Dauid:</hi> and ſurely it is one of the markes of the man that ſhall haue place in the holy mount, euen to make much of them that feare the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. The contrary vnto this the Apoſtle reproues, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. when hee would not haue vs to haue the graces of God in reſpect of perſons; we honour ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and make an Idoll of earthly pompe, but as for the Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, we rather expoſe them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16364:29"/>then make them neere vnto vs: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſubiect in hand points vnto the graue; I will returne vnto a Vſe that ſhall ſpeake the ſame language.</p>
            <p>Are the righteous the onely men with God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> and ſo precious, that their very graues are perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and their deaths ſo regarded? O then, this bids all the godly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the conſideration of a diſſolution with good reſolution: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny motiues will be ready for vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we dye not total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16364:30"/>it is but the body that is ſtrooke downe, the ſoule is immortall; which like the Doue, could find no reſt for the ſoale of her foote, vntill ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned vnto the Arke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. ſo verily, there is no true reſt for the ſoule of man, vntill it returne to that God that infuſed it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we dye not perpetually; we ſhall be put into the darke houſe for a time, but there is a day, a bleſſed day, euen the day of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then comes that coniunction, and re-vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16364:30"/>of both againe; now then death cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent or alter that marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age day: for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>What ſhall ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from the loue of Chriſt Ieſus? ſhall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall Principalities, ſhall powers, ſhall things preſent or things to come, ſhall life or death? no, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall remoue vs from the lone of Chriſt Ieſus, Rom.</hi> 8.39.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſting and poyſon of death is taken away, (Chriſt Ieſus) like a triumphant Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, hath ſubdued: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>matum eſt,</hi> it is finiſhed,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16364:31"/>and the debt paid, and the hand-writing that was againſt vs, faſtened to his Croſſe, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.14. now then put it to the queſtion, why ſhall wee feare to dye?</p>
            <p>I deny not, but nature hath trembles in the very beſt of vs vntill we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it by grace and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine meditations: we doe at death as <hi>Moſes</hi> did with his rod, who when hee ſaw it turned into a ſerpent, <hi>primo intuitu,</hi> he ſtarted from it, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards goes neere vnto it, takes it vp, and makes vſe of it; ſo wee indeede at
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16364:31"/>the firſt, vntill wee ſee death diſarmed, ſtart from it, but afterwards finding that Chriſt hath gotten victorie ouer the graue, and that the ſting is gone as the challing ſhewes <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. then with <hi>Moſes</hi> we draw neer and ſurrender into the hands of the Lord beeing but tenents at will; then wee can take the rod and make good vſe of it as he did. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe that feare to dye notwithſtanding theſe comforts, if wee ſhould enter into their reaſons they muſt needes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16364:32"/>be dreadfull, as</p>
            <p>Firſt, either they haue not taſted of the life to come, and ſo are lothe to change this preſent life; or elſe they haue not dyed aforehand, that is, conſidered of death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came; or elſe third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they haue carried their bane, euill conſciences, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. We will take view of theſe reaſons by themſelues.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of them, their not taſting of the life to come; indeede their caſe is miſerable, for they liue onely in body and cannot ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16364:32"/>
               <hi>I liue by Faith in the Sonne of God, Galat.</hi> 2.20. Theſe men muſt haue their ſoules beaten out or driuen out of them, as wee finde of the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites eſtate in the 27. of <hi>Iob, What hope hath hee,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>when God ſhall beate out his ſoule?</hi> Indeede ſuch men ſing loath to depart; for here was their bliſſe, and to be taken from hence, being aliens and ſtrangers from the life of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. alas, what ſhall they doe. As for thoſe that haue not dyed afore hand, it muſt needes be as terrible to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16364:33"/>them: how many greets and re-greets paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God, and the ſoules of the faithfull? <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to be diſſolued and to be with God, which is beſt of all, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. and the bleſſed Apoſtle tels vs, that by the reioycing that he hath in Chriſt, he dyes dayly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. He num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers his dayes, and ſo, that he may apply his heart vnto wiſedome, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> prayes, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 90. this ſpirituall Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke is a good know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but the prophane and carnall men, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to meete with no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16364:33"/>ſuch reckoning: this not dying afore-hand, makes many ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binde-hand with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but let <hi>Hadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Emperour be an example vnto them; it is ſtoried of him, that death comming, and he not expecting, and when the diuorce betwixt the body and ſoule was to be executed, hee cryes out, as amazed, <hi>O ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nula, vagula, blandula, quae nunc abibis in loca?</hi> O my poore ſoule, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther art thou going? Doth hee aske of his hopes then, when the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16364:34"/>partition was to bee made? A poore ſoule indeed, for all his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: If therefore wee would not bee ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, let vs bee prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Now laſt of all, which is not leaſt of all, but rather worſt of all, comes they, who are loath to dye, becauſe they carry their bane about them; and that is, an euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, this puts them vpon the racke, and tortures all parts; this makes their caſe like vnto the ſtrooke Deare,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16364:34"/>the arrow ſhee hath at her heart, and yet skips vp and downe, but carryes that about her, that will diſpatch her: ſo is it with an euill conſcience, well they may skippe vp and downe, but they haue that at the heart of them, that will make all vncomfortable: and no meruaile, <hi>for a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit, who can beare?</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon:</hi> This gaue, as <hi>Folydore Virgill</hi> obſerues, King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, more wounds in his dreame, the night before, then hee had the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16364:35"/>next day in the field: Well, let vs all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, pray, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour for good conſciences, this makes a continuall feaſt; this ſends vs with boldneſſe to the throne of grace, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. In a word, this will make vs both in life and death, fit for CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, whoſe wee are, and not our owne, and therefore ought to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God both in our bodies and ſoules, which were redeemed with the precious bloud of IESVS CHRIST,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16364:35"/>through whom we haue redemption, euen the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. And thus much ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to bee ſpoken for our inſtruction, who are in our way towards God, now a word or two of him who is already gone to GOD.</p>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:16364:36"/>
               <head>The Teſtimony of him that liued and dyed in the Faith of Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
               <p>VVEE doe reade of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches and others, that after their deaths, they were embalmed, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 50.2. but this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man embalmed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aliue; I ſpeake it according to the ſenſe of <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. <hi>A good name,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is as a precious oyntment;</hi> many ſweete odours belongs vnto it, which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16364:36"/>time can neither waſh nor waſte away; <hi>Nam virtus poſt funera viuit.</hi> Thus did this hopefull young Gentleman fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the tracke of the Elders, who by Faith obtained a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.2. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> like it was with him, of whom Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes largely in his third Epiſtle: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius,</hi> ſaith he, hath a good report of all men; yea, and of the truth it ſelfe. If any that knew not this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, would preſſe the reaſon of his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16364:37"/>anſwere will be made, that if ſincerity in his Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igion, induſtry in his Vocation, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fability in Conuerſation might giue their voyces, it will be no ſinne to ſay, this was a gracious youth.</p>
               <p>And firſt for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: He was not with <hi>Agrippa,</hi> almoſt a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, nor yet with <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea</hi> luke-warme in his profeſſion, but found in al true tenents of the faith, worſhiping that one and onely God, from whence ſaluation comes to men.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:16364:37"/>
               <p>As for his Vocation, with a diligent hand and faithfull heart hee went about it; his gaine therein was godlineſſe, which the Apoſtle ſaith is great gaines, if men be content with that they haue, 1 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 6. Surely hee was content for peace-ſake to paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his profits many times, and to end mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at home, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences that might ariſe in poynt of law.</p>
               <p>If all that were towards the law had the ſame heart, ſurely that calling
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16364:38"/>would haue a great part of that bleſſing which CHRIST pronounceth, <hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> Bleſſed are the peace-makers <hi>Mat.</hi> 5 For ſurely the law is good and ſurely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to diſtribute, or <hi>dare ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cuique,</hi> to giue to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that which is his, had a good ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and therefore they ſhall doe well, who haue other mens cauſes to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to remember that one day, their owne cauſe ſhall come before the Iudge: This yong Lawyer did ſo, being
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16364:38"/>tender in his conſcience, and vpright in the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he vndertooke.</p>
               <p>As for his Conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was ſuch that all that knew him did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him: for hee had matter, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded things with good iudgement, and then the manner of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe was ſo affable as that hee found fauour whereſoeuer he came, which is the bleſſing promiſed, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16. <hi>When a mans wayes doe pleaſe the Lord, hee will make his enemies to be his friends:</hi> In a word hee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16364:39"/>was to his deare mother, a right <hi>Barnabas;</hi> that is, a Sonne of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſo the word ſignifieth; he was grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou, with men, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious with God, he did liue the life of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and did dye the death of the righteous; he is gone before, and wee ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: In which progreſſe let vs end.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16364:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
